Finding Aid for the Stanley Chase Papers LSC.1090
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 1: Theater, 1946-1989.; 34 boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 4 map folders.
  - Subseries 1A: The Threepenny Opera, 1952-1961.; 13 boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 map folder.
    - MGM LP cover., 1954. (Box 71, Folder 2)
      Duplicate copies of the record cover featuring a color image of the cast from the Theatre De Lys production.
    - Set design illustration., 1953 March 9. (Box 71, Folder 3)
      Original watercolor drawing by William Pitkin.
    - Original watercolor character sketch., no date. (Box 71, Folder 4)
      Original drawing for The Threepenny Opera, which appeared in the New York Times to celebrate the 2000th performance at the Theatre de Lys.
    - Character rendering and posters., ca. 1955. (Box 71, Folder 5)
      Black line sketch of Mack the Knife and Jenny, used for advertisements (included).
    - Norkin character illustration., ca. 1955. (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Scrapbooks., 1960. (Box 65)
      Two scrapbooks of the The Threepenny Opera advertising campaigns.
    - Advertising posters., ca. 1955-1960. (Box 95)
      Oversize advertisements for The Threepenny Opera mounted on board.
    - Photographs., ca. 1955-1960. (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
    - Programs and publicity., 1954-1961. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Threepenny Productions financial summaries., 1957-1961. (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
    - Advertising and publicity sketches., ca. 1954-1960. (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Reproductions.
    - Opening night telegrams., 1955. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Original program layouts., ca. 1954. (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Copyright lawsuit., 1955. (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Theatre de Lys liscencing., 1954. (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Clippings., ca. 1954. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Clippings., ca. 1954-1961. (Box 13, Folder 1-7)
  - Subseries 1B: Free and Easy, 1956-1960.; 6 boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 map folder.
    This subseries consists of production and business files, posters, press clippings, and scripts for the European tour of Free and Easy, produced by Stanley Chase. Clippings are in German and French. The production was a Harold Arlen and Johnny Mercer jazz musical featuring Quincy Jones. For audio recordings of the cast production, see Series 4. Audio and visual materials.
    - Notes and correspondence., ca. 1959. (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Handwritten notes and some correspondence related to various issues with the production.
    - Contracts, correspondence, and legal documents., 1959-1960. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Actors' Equity Association and cast., 1959-1960. (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Correspondence related to cast.
    - Budgets., 1958. (Box 14, Folder 4)
      Pre-production budget projections, broken down by touring location (U.S. and Europe) and by week.
    - Ardstone, Inc., 1959. (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and contracts related to an investment made in the production.
    - Berman, Abraham., 1959-1960. (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Correspondence related to Mr. Arlen and Mr. Mercer's interest in the production. Mr. Berman was the attorney for Arlen and Mercer.
    - Contracts., 1959. (Box 14, Folder 7)
      Correspondence and contracts related to Arna Bontemps and the estate of Countee Cullen.
    - Breens, Robert--Contracts., 1956-1959. (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Draft versions and contracts related to Breens' participation in the production including business certificate and contract.
    - Breens, Robert--Correspondence., 1959. (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Correspondence related to the Breens' activities with the production.
    - Breens, Robert--Termination., 1959. (Box 14, Folder 10)
      Correspondence from cast regarding Breens' removal from the production.
    - Playbills., 1959. (Box 14, Folder 11)
      Oversize French and German playbills.
    - Legal documents and correspondence., 1959-1964. (Box 14, Folder 12)
      Copy of Chase's testimony in Crown Holding Company v. Stanley Chase and related papers regarding Free and Easy financing and contracts.
    - Scrapbook., 1959. (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
      Scrapbook of press clippings from international sources.
    - Clippings., 1959-1960. (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
      Clipped newspaper articles from international and domestic sources.
    - Publicity., 1959-1960. (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Correspondence and press releases related to publicity for the production.
    - Publications., 1959-1960. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      Whole copies of papers and magazines with articles on Free and Easy.
    - Handbills., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Costume and scenery notes., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Expenditures and contracts., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Miscellanous correspondence and contracts., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Removed from a folder labeled "C. Stevens: Private and personal, current." Letters and papers relate to Free and Easy production.
    - Script., ca. 1959. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Musicians., 1959-1960. (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Correspondence related to musicians.
    - Musicians' contracts., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 7)
      Signed contracts and draft of contracts regarding employment of musicians.
    - Office memoranda., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Memos and messages from production staff and management.
    - Music index., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 9)
      Draft index of musical numbers.
    - Theater and bookings., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 10)
      Correspondence related to venue use and preview bookings.
    - Advertisement requests., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 11)
      Requests from organizations regarding advertisement sales.
    - Davis, Sammy, Jr., 1959-1960. (Box 16, Folder 12)
      Documents, correspondence and contracts.
    - Ashley-Steiner Corporation., 1957-1959. (Box 16, Folder 13)
      Correspondence and contracts related to representation by the Ashley-Steiner corporation of the exploitation of Free and Easy.
    - Applications., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 14)
      Correspondence regarding employment and casting.
    - Crane, Earl., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 15)
      Correspondence related to an investment in the production.
    - Harrison, Kay., 1959. (Box 16, Folder 16)
      Correspondence related to the planning of the film production version of "Free and Easy" in Europe.
    - Arlen, Harold., 1959. (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Correspondence related to the production.
    - Bookings., 1956, 1959. (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Correspondence related to non-European bookings of the production.
    - Casting., 1959. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and materials related to casting.
    - Costumes and fabrics., 1959. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Correspondence and documentation related to the acquisition of costumes and fabric for the production.
    - Production staff., 1959-1960. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Contracts and correspondence related to production crew.
    - Investor log., ca. 1959. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      Log book with the names and investments of limited partners.
    - Legal correspondence., 1959-1960. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      Correspondence and documents related to legal, financial and contractual issues.
    - Financial records and contracts., 1959-1960. (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Credits., ca. 1959. (Box 17, Folder 9)
      Draft versions of the production credits.
    - Investors., 1959-1960. (Box 17, Folder 10)
      Correspondence related to limited partnership investments in the production.
    - Cast contracts., ca. 1959. (Box 17, Folder 11)
      Documentation and contract rider related to cast contracts.
    - Props., 1959. (Box 17, Folder 12)
      Correspondence related to the acquisition of stage props for the production.
    - Poster art., ca. 1959. (Box 17, Folder 13)
      Small-format original painted mock-ups for promotional posters.
    - Scrapbook., 1959. (Box 17, Folder 14)
      Scrapbook of news clippings about Free and Easy.
    - Investors., 1959-1960. (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
    - Limited partnership agreement., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Unsigned contracts used for investors.
    - Salisbury, Leah., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Correspondence with the representative of the authors' estates.
    - Stillman, David., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Correspondence regarding capitalization of the production.
    - Kaufman, Joe., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Correspondence related to investment in the production.
    - Lucius Smith III Associates., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Correspondence and contracts related to Mr. Smith's activities as an investment and government relations consultant to the production.
    - Mercury Record deal., 1958-1959. (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Correspondence and contracts related to the recording of the original cast album.
    - Manufacturers' Trust Company., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 9)
      Correspondence and contracts related to accounts held by the production with the Trust Company.
    - Williams, Irene., 1959-1960. (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Set memos., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 11)
      Memos related to production.
    - Press and invitation lists., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 12)
      Correspondence and documentation related to invitations to various performances.
    - Travel documents., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 13)
      Correspondence and documents related to travel arrangements for production.
    - Press correspondence., 1959. (Box 18, Folder 14)
      Correspondence related to press and press coverage of the production.
    - Press releases and statements., ca. 1959-1960. (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Feather, Leonard., ca. 1959. (Box 18, Folder 16)
      Manuscripts and typewritten copies of "The Blues"; miscellaneous character lists and press statements.
    - Synopsis and clippings., ca. 1959. (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Audition notes., ca. 1959. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Publicity draft., ca. 1959. (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Draft pages from a document describing the production's relevance to American culture.
    - Letter from Bobby [?]., 1959 March 16. (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Letter from a colleague signed Bobby, regarding his opinions on contemporary theater, and congratulating Chase on the development of Free and Easy. Includes duscussion of title change.
    - Photographs., 1959. (Box 19, Folder 4-6)
      Black and white photographs of the cast and set, including production and head shots. For one additional oversize photograph, see box 62.
    - French and German newspapers., ca. 1959-1960. (Box 62, Folder 1-2)
    - French publicity posters., ca. 1959. (Box 62, Folder 3)
      Alhambra Theatre productions publicity.
    - Set design illustrations., 1959. (Box 62, Folder 4)
      Original watercolor drawings.
    - Free and Easy French publicity posters., 1959. (Box 72)
      Alhambra Theatre productions publicity for Free and Easy and "Opéra de Pékin."
  - Subseries 1C: Bijou Theatre files, 1946-1961.; 6.5 boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 2 map folders.
    This subseries consists of production files and business files, original set design illustrations, posters, press clippings, ephemera, and scripts for three Broadway plays produced by Stanley Chase at the Bijou Theatre: Eugene O'Neill's A Moon for the Misbegotten, Graham Greene's The Potting Shed, and William Saroyan's The Cave Dwellers. The subseries also includes miscellaneous files for other plays under consideration at the Bijou during this period. The original order of the files was maintained at the time of processing.
    - The Potting Shed--Stage and set design plans., 1957. (Box 74)
      Includes light plot, elevations and stage designs, and an original watercolor on paper by William Pitkin.
    - The Potting Shed--Playbills., 1957. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Programs from the production at the Bijou Theatre and the John Golden Theater.
    - The Potting Shed--Cast photographs., 1957. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Photographs and some biographical statements of the cast.
    - The Potting Shed--Proof sheets of set and cast., 1957. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Photographs of the set with and without the cast. See box 61 for an oversize portfolio of stills from the production.
    - The Potting Shed--Negatives., 1957. (Box 20, Folder 4)
      Negatives of the set, possibly for lighting design.
    - The Potting Shed--Contracts, permits and correspondence related to cast and crew., 1956, 1957. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      Contracts and permits with crew, cast, and Graham Greene and related correspondence.
    - The Potting Shed--Summary of operations., 1957, 1958. (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Operations summaries by CPA firm, weekly statements and correspondence and statements of operations.
    - The Potting Shed--Correspondence and contracts for the Actors' Equity Association., 1956-1957. (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - The Potting Shed--Clippings., 1956-1957. (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
    - The Potting Shed--Box office statements., 1957. (Box 21, Folder 5-6)
    - The Potting Shed--Script., no date. (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - The Potting Shed--Casting and rehearsals., 1956-1957. (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Correspondence and miscellaneous documents related to casting and rehearsals.
    - The Potting Shed--Correspondence related to cast and crew., 1956-1957. (Box 23, Folder 2)
      Correspondence related to contracts, travel, immigration and other employment issues.
    - The Potting Shed--Props and costumes., 1956-1957. (Box 23, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and contractual agreements related to the acquisition of props and costumes and other theatrical equipment.
    - The Potting Shed--Van Loewen, Jan., 1956-1957. (Box 23, Folder 4)
      Correspondence from and related to Dr. Jan Van Loewen regarding copyright issues.
    - The Potting Shed--Royalties and Salary Statements., 1957. (Box 23, Folder 5)
      Correspondences related to payments to Mr. Greene and some cast members.
    - The Potting Shed--Rights Inquiries., 1957. (Box 23, Folder 6)
      Correspondence related to requests to produce play outside of New York.
    - The Potting Shed--Tickets requests and invitation lists., 1956-1957. (Box 23, Folder 7)
      Correspondence and lists related to ticket sales and comp tickets for press and other guests.
    - The Potting Shed--Publicity materials., 1957. (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - The Potting Shed--Marketing and Marquee materials., 1957. (Box 23, Folder 9)
      Comps for print ads and materials related to credits and publicity in theater and on marquee. See box 75 for publicity posters and the original poster artwork.
    - The Potting Shed--Script and corrections., 1957. (Box 23, Folder 10)
      A copy of Eugene O'Neill's script, and corrections submitted by Graham Greene to Mr. Capalbo.
    - The Potting Shed--Production book. (Box 23, Folder 11)
      Script with notes on staging, light plots, etc.
    - The Potting Shed--Correspondence., 1956-1958. (Box 23, Folder 12)
      Correspondence and telegrams related to a number of issues.
    - A Moon for the Misbegotten--Miscellaneous., 1957. (Box 23, Folder 13)
      Newspaper and print clippings, correspondence, contracts, playbills and auditing statements related to production. See box 66 for oversize photographic stills of the set.
    - A Moon for the Misbegotten--Clippings., 1957. (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - A Moon for the Misbegotten--Scrapbook., 1957. (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - A Moon for the Misbegotten--Oversize., 1957. (Box 80)
      Draft of publicity poster, matted; original watercolor set design illustration by by William Pitkin.
    - The Cave Dwellers--Set design illustration., 1957. (Box 74)
      Original watercolor on paper by William Pitkin.
    - The Cave Dwellers--Miscellaneous., 1955-1958. (Box 22, Folder 1)
      Documents include financial summaries, playbills, correspondence, notes and newspaper clippings related to the production. See box 66 for oversize photographic stills of the cast and set.
    - The Cave Dwellers--Contact sheets., ca. 1957. (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Contact sheets of portraits of cast and producers.
    - The Cave Dwellers--Clippings., 1957. (Box 22, Folder 3-4)
    - The Cave Dwellers--Bear costume., 1958. (Box 22, Folder 5)
      Correspondence related to the rental of a bear costume for the production.
    - Authors' contracts and Dramatist Guild., 1954-1955. (Box 22, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and contracts related to A Moon for the Misbegotten, Purple Dust and William Saroyan (A Moon for the Misbegotten). File also includes numerous documents from the Dramatists' Guild.
    - Advertiser Inquiries., 1956-1959. (Box 22, Folder 7)
      Correspondence from organizations inquiring about advertising sales.
    - Rhoade, Max., 1957. (Box 22, Folder 8)
      Correspondence and documents related to information on venue leasing.
    - Subscription plan., 1957-1958. (Box 22, Folder 9)
      Correspondence and documents related to the Bijou Theatre series ticket subscription plan.
    - Theatre parties., 1956-1957. (Box 22, Folder 10)
      Correspondence, contracts and documents related to theatre party sales.
    - Unions., 1956-1957. (Box 22, Folder 11)
      Correspondence and documents related to union represented employees.
    - Billing statements., 1957-1958. (Box 22, Folder 12)
      Correspondence, contracts and billing statements related to the rental of lighting equipment and the purchasing of frames.
    - Actors' Equity., 1957-1958. (Box 22, Folder 13)
      Correspondence and governance rules.
    - Advertising copy., 1946-1955. (Box 22, Folder 14)
      Drafts of ad copy, including an original rendering of the program for Moon for the Misbegotton, and advertisements from other theater series and productions.
    - Capalbo-Chase partnership dissolution., 1958. (Box 22, Folder 15)
      Correspondence related to the end of the business relationship between Chase and Capalbo.
    - Handwritten notes., 1957. (Box 22, Folder 16)
      Assorted notes by Chase on Bijou productions.
    - Jellico, Jimmy., 1957-1958. (Box 24, Folder 1)
      Correspondence related to the recording of "Jimmy Jellico," a musical composition inspired by the play The Cave Dwellers.
    - Ashley-Steiner., 1957-1958. (Box 24, Folder 2)
      Correspondence related to the organization contracted to handle financing negotiations for Chase and Capalbo.
    - Blackburn, Audrey., 1957-1958. (Box 24, Folder 3)
      Correspondence related to numerous issues and productions.
    - City Investment Company., 1956-1958. (Box 24, Folder 4)
      Correspondence related to the rental of the Bijou. City Investment was the management company responsible for the theatre's lease.
    - "How Mr. Hogan Robbed a Bank.", ca. 1956. (Box 24, Folder 5)
      Script for John Steinbeck's one-act.
    - Summary of Operations., 1954-1957. (Box 24, Folder 6)
      Audit statements for The Threepenny Opera and The Potting Shed from Benjamin Friedman, CPA.
    - Trade periodicals., 1951, 1957. (Box 24, Folder 7)
      Two trade magazines; one with interior dimensions and charts for the Bijou Theatre, and the other with an article on the Bijou series produced by Chase and Capalbo.
    - Notes., ca. 1956. (Box 24, Folder 8)
      Numerous handwritten notes.
    - Miscellanous publicity., 1954-1961. (Box 24, Folder 9)
      Assorted playbills and clippings related to Bijou productions.
    - Essay by William Saroyan., no date. (Box 24, Folder 10)
      Typewritten essay on playwrights.
    - Photographs of Stanley Chase., ca. 1954-1961. (Box 24, Folder 11)
      Assorted contact sheets and 8" x 10" black and white portraits of Stanley Chase, on and off the sets of his productions. One signed artistic rendering of Chase's profile. For oversize photos of Chase from approximately this period, see box 66.
    - Personal correspondence., 1956-1959.; [2 folders]. (Box 24, Folder 12-13)
      Correspondence related to Chase's personal and professional life, including letters from Dorothy Rice, his wife, friends, and colleagues from the theater world.
    - Advance ticket sale., 1954. (Box 25, Folder 1)
      Handwritten documents with financial data.
    - Art movie project., 1954. (Box 25, Folder 2)
      Type-written document with a list of films.
    - Investors' correspondence., 1956-1959. (Box 25, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and contracts related to limited partnership investments.
    - Job applications., 1954. (Box 25, Folder 4)
      Correspondence related to employment.
    - Budgets., 1954-1957. (Box 25, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and documents related the budgeting of the Bijou Theatre series.
    - Ensemble., 1954. (Box 25, Folder 6)
      Investment portfolio and documents related to The Ensemble Company, a New York limited partnership company organized to produce plays in repertory.
    - Script coverage., 1956-1957. (Box 25, Folder 7)
      Coverage related to projects submitted or pursued by Chase.
    - Fitelson and Mayers., 1954-1955. (Box 25, Folder 8)
      Correspondence related to legal issues and billing.
    - Manufacturers Trust Company., 1954-1958. (Box 25, Folder 9)
      Endorsed checks and a bank statement, and credit advice statements.
    - New York Department of Labor., 1954. (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Documents related to workmen's compensation claims.
    - Insurance., 1954-1955. (Box 25, Folder 11)
      Documents related to insurance coverage.
    - Investment agreements., 1954. (Box 25, Folder 12)
      Correspondence, contacts and documents related to limited investment agreements.
    - Investors' correspondence., 1954-1955. (Box 25, Folder 13)
      Correspondence related to limited partnership investments.
    - Copeland, Lammot Du P., 1954 April 14. (Box 25, Folder 14)
      Letter regarding a production of L'Etat de Siege.
    - League of New York Theatres., 1957. (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Correspondence and contracts related to general theatre operations and unions.
    - New scripts., 1956-1958. (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Correspondence related to scripts submitted for perusal and potential exploitation or pursued as such by Chase and Capalbo.
    - London trip., 1956. (Box 26, Folder 3)
      Correspondence, billing statements and documents related to a business trip taken by Mr. Capalbo.
    - Capstan Company Limited Partnership., 1956-1957. (Box 26, Folder 4)
      Contracts and correspondence related to the formation of Capstan Company.
    - Mother Courage., 1956-1957. (Box 26, Folder 5)
      Correspondence related to the attempted acquisition of rights to Brecht's play.
    - Personnel and production staff., 1956-1958. (Box 26, Folder 6)
      Correspondence related to production staff.
    - ANTA Correspondence., 1954. (Box 26, Folder 7)
      Correspondence regarding a request for potential financial assistance from ANTA for the Bijou series.
    - Bijou series proposal., 1954 September 10. (Box 26, Folder 8)
      Origional proposal for Bijou productions, by Capalbo and Chase.
    - Bijou Theatre productions posters., ca. 1955-1958. (Box 75)
      Posters for The Potting Shed, Moon for the Misbegotton, and The Cave Dwellers.
  - Subseries 1D: Miscellaneous, 1953-1989.; 3.5 boxes.
    This subseries contains correspondence and production files for miscellaneous plays (most never produced), and assorted theatrical scripts.
    - All Women Are One., 1957-1958. (Box 26, Folder 9)
      Contracts, correspondence and related materials for the attempted production of Ben Kerner's play.
    - "Heartbreak House.", 1956-1958. (Box 26, Folder 10)
      Correspondence, clippings and contracts related to the optioning of this performance piece, casting, budget and costumes.
    - Miscellaneous production budgets., ca. 1953-1954. (Box 26, Folder 11)
      Estimated production budgets and budget documentation related to productions not produced by Chase. Some of these documents are not dated.
    - Plays submitted., 1955-1959. (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Waiting for Godot--Correspondence., 1955. (Box 27, Folder 2)